Byzantine Institute, Inc. Dumbarton Oaks Research Library and Collection. The Byzantine Institute and Dumbarton Oaks Fieldwork Records and Papers, ca. late 1920s-2000s: Finding Aid
Image Collections and Fieldwork Archives, Dumbarton Oaks Research Library and Collection
- Fieldwork Papers, 1920s -2000s, MS.BZ.004-02; 46 boxes including 494 folders; 29 boxes including 29 photo albums; 20+ oversize files; 26 boxes of backlog materials; 2 boxes including 14 folders of accumulated research materials by ICFA staff
  - Oversize Paper Materials, 1910s-1950s, MS.BZ.004-02-05; 2 boxes including 20 oversize files
    - Oversize: Large, 1929-1950s, MS.BZ.004-02-05-02; 1 box including 11 oversize folders; Elizabeth S. Bolman, ed., Monastic Visions: Wall Paintings in the Monastery of St. Anthony at the Red Sea (New Haven, CT and London: American Research Center in Egypt, Inc. and Yale University Press, 2002), x
      - Watercolors, copied from the walls in the khurus, St. Anthony, Red Sea Monasteries, by Vladimir Netchetailov, [ca. 1929-1931], MS.BZ.004-02-05-02-558; 1 oversize folder with 4 original watercolors
        - “Saint Mercurius”, [ca. 1929-1931], MS.BZ.004-02-05-02-558-001; 2 watercolor paintings
          Consists of left section and right section - accession numbers: BF.F.1993.F1961 and BF.F.1993.F1963, respectively
          Accession numbers: BF.F.1993.F1961 and BF.F.1993.F1963
        - “Palace of Nebuchadnezzar”, [ca. 1929-1931], MS.BZ.004-02-05-02-558-002; 1 watercolor painting
          Accession number: BF.F.1993.F1962
        - “Saint George riding a horse”, [ca. 1929-1931], MS.BZ.004-02-05-02-558-003; 1 watercolor painting
          Accession number: BF.F.1993.F1960
      - Watercolors, copied from the walls in the khurus, St. Anthony, Red Sea Monasteries, Egypt by Vladimir Netchetailov, [ca. 1929-1931], MS.BZ.004-02-05-02-559; 1 oversize folder with 5 original watercolors
        - “Meeting of Christ and women in the garden”, [ca. 1929-1931], MS.BZ.004-02-05-02-559-001; 2 watercolor paintings
          Consists of top section and bottom section; accession numbers: BF.F.1993.F1971 and BF.F.1993.F1972, respectively.
          Accession numbers: BF.F.1993.F1971 and BF.F.1993.F1972
        - Women at the tomb, Figure of angel, [ca. 1929-1931], MS.BZ.004-02-05-02-559-002; 2 watercolor paintings
          Consists of left section and right section; accession numbers: BF.F.1993.F1973a and B.F.1993.F1973, respectively.
          Accession numbers: BF.F.1993.F1973 and BF.F.1993.F1973a
        - Women at the tomb, [ca. 1929-1931], MS.BZ.004-02-05-02-559-003; 1 watercolor painting
          Accession number: BF.F.1993.F1988
      - Watercolors, copied from the walls in the khurus, St. Anthony, Red Sea Monasteries, Egypt by Vladimir Netchetailov, [ca. 1929-1931], MS.BZ.004-02-05-02-560; 1 oversize folder with 8 original watercolor paintings
        - Saint Michael the Archangel, [ca. 1929-1931], MS.BZ.004-02-05-02-560-001; 8 watercolor paintings
          Large figure, consisting of the following components:
          Head (accession number: BF.F.1993.F1974)
          Top middle section (accession number: BF.F.1993.F1975)
          Bottom middle section (accession number: BF.F.1993.F1976)
          Bottom section (accession number: BF.F.1993.F1977)
          Right section (accession number: BF.F.1993.F1970)
          Right section (accession number: BF.F.1993.F1968)
          Right section (accession number: BF.F.1993.F1965)
          Right section (accession number: BF.F.1993.F1966)
          Accession numbers: BF.F.1993.F1965-.F1966, BF.F.1993.F1968, BF.F.1993.F1970, BF.F.1993.F1974-.F1977.
      - Watercolor, copied from the walls in the khurus, St. Anthony, Red Sea Monasteries, Egypt by Vladimir Netchetailov, [ca. 1929-1931], MS.BZ.004-02-05-02-561; 1 oversize folder with 1 original watercolor painting
        - Vine scrolls, [ca. 1929-1931], MS.BZ.004-02-05-02-561-001; 1 watercolor painting
          Accession number: BF.F.1993.F1981
      - Watercolors, copied from the walls in the sanctuary, St. Anthony, Red Sea Monasteries, Egypt by Vladimir Netchetailov, [ca. 1929-1931], MS.BZ.004-02-05-02-562; 1 oversize folder with 4 original watercolors
        - Sacrifice of Abraham, [ca. 1929-1931], MS.BZ.004-02-05-02-562-001; 1 watercolor painting
          Accession number: BF.F.1993.F1991
        - Anonymous patriarch, [ca. 1929-1931], MS.BZ.004-02-05-02-562-002; 1 watercolor paintings
          Consists of top section and bottom section; accession numbers: BF.F.1993.F1993 and BF.F.1993.F1992, respectively.
          Accession numbers: BF.F.1993.F1992 and BF.F.1993.F1993
          For color reproductions of the watercolor, see Subgroup 2, Series 5, Subseries 1, File 549, Item 3.
        - Peter of Alexandria, [ca. 1929-1931], MS.BZ.004-02-05-02-562-003; 1 watercolor painting
          Accession number: BF.F.1993.F1994
          For color reproductions of the watercolor, see Subgroup 2, Series 5, Subseries 1, File 549, Item 4.
      - Watercolors, copied from the walls in the chapel, St. Anthony, Red Sea Monasteries, Egypt by Vladimir Netchetailov, [ca. 1929-1931], MS.BZ.004-02-05-02-563; 1 oversize folder with 4 original watercolor paintings
        - Cross flanked by angels, [ca. 1929-1931], MS.BZ.004-02-05-02-563-001; 1 watercolor painting
          Accession number: BF.F.1993.F1969
          For color reproductions of the watercolor, see Subgroup 2, Series 5, Subseries 1, File 549, Item 1.
        - The Deësis, [ca. 1929-1931], MS.BZ.004-02-05-02-563-002; 3 watercolor paintings
          Scene consists of the following components:
          Virgin Mary with two animals (left section; accession number: BF.F.1993.F1979)
          Christ enthroned in mandorla with four angels (middle section; accession number: BF.F.1993.1978)
          John the Baptist with two animals (right section; accession number: BF.F.1993.F1980)
          Accession numbers: BF.F.1993.F1979-.F1980
      - Monastery of St. Anthony, Red Sea Monasteries, Egypt, [ca. 1929-1931], MS.BZ.004-02-05-02-564; 1 oversize folder with 1 drawing
        - Overhead plan: “Group plan of New Church, Old Church and Tower. Indicated A, B and C on Plot Plan”, [ca. 1929-1931], MS.BZ.004-02-05-02-564-001; 1 architectural drawing
          Accession number: BF.F.1993.F1987
      - Watercolor, St. Paul, Red Sea Monasteries, Egypt by Vladimir Netchetailov, [ca. 1929-1931], MS.BZ.004-02-05-02-565; 1 oversize folder with 2 original watercolor paintings
        - Saint riding a horse, [ca. 1929-1931], MS.BZ.004-02-05-02-565-001; 2 watercolor paintings
          Consists of left section and right section; accession numbers: BF.F.1993.F920 and BF.F.1993.F1964, respectively.
          Accession numbers: BF.F.1993.F920 and BF.F.1993.F1964
      - Architectural drawings, Kariye Camii, Istanbul, Turkey, undated, MS.BZ.004-02-05-02-566; 1 oversize folder with 5 architectural drawings
        Donated to ICFA from Robert Ousterhout in September 2012.
        Robert Ousterhout obtained these items from the American Research Center in Turkey (ARIT-Istanbul) in the mid-1990s.
        These items correspond to the report: “TRAVAUX DE CONSOLIDATION DE LA MOSQUEE KAHRİYE: NOTICE DES CONSTATATIONS FAITES SUR LES LIEUX,” May 1954 - See Subgroup 2, Series 2, Subseries 5, File 398.
      - Architectural drawings and photographs of maps, Bargala, Republic of Macedonia, undated, MS.BZ.004-02-05-02-567; 1 oversize folder with 7 items
        Accession numbers: BF.F.1993.F994-.F1000
Addendum: Accumulated Research Materials by ICFA Staff
These materials were compiled by the ICFA staff during the processing of this collection. These items were used to help write the acquisition history and historical note of the Byzantine Institute and Dumbarton Oaks fieldwork projects. Box: 1 Collection Guides
Folder 1: Document/item removal forms and archives transfer forms
Folder 2: Finding aid (black book) by Jeff Schlossberg, ca. 1982 (Folder 1 of 4)
Folder 3: Copy of the finding aid (red binder) by Jeff Schlossberg, ca. 1982 (Folder 2 of 4) - Folder 4: Copy of finding aid by Jeff Schlossberg, ca. 1982 (Folder 3 of 4)
Folder 5: Copy of finding aid by Jeff Schlossberg, ca. 1982 (Folder 4 of 4)
Folder 6: Draft of finding aid by Jeff Schlossberg, ca. 1982
Folder 7: Copies of inventories, 1950s - Photocopies of inventory lists and correspondence regarding the transfer of materials from the Byzantine Institute Library in Paris to Dumbarton Oaks
Box 2: Articles, Publications, and Resources Contains copies of published articles and archival materials from various repositories, such as the Image Collections and Fieldwork Archives at Dumbarton Oaks and Harvard University Archives
Folder 8: Thomas Whittemore and the Byzantine Institute, historical and literary sources - Contains copies of articles or excerpts that pertain to Thomas Whittemore, from the Dumbarton Oaks Papers, the Harvard Crimson, and other sources. Also includes copies of: “Convoy to West Africa” by Graham Greene, “Remote People” by Evelyn Waugh, “The Elusive Mr. Whittemore, the Early Years,” by Holger Klein, and others. Also contains photocopies of correspondence relating to Whittemore from the Robert Van Nice collection, also in ICFA.
Folder 9: Notes produced by Natalia Teteriatnikov - Contains photographs of Thomas Whittemore, correspondence with William MacDonald and others, internal memos, and various notes about the collection including its conservation. Teteriatnikov was the former curator of the Byzantine Photograph and Fieldwork Archive from 1986 to 2007.
Folder 10: “Inventory of Samples taken from Hagia Sophia by the Byzantine Institute”
Folder 11: Copies of articles related to Alexandre Piankoff - Contains “Deux peintures de Saints Militaires au Monastère de Saint Antoine,” Les Cahiers Coptes 10 (1956): 17-25.
Folder 12: Materials related to the Byzantine Institute from the Dumbarton Oaks Archives - Contains meeting summaries and correspondence, [ca. 1945-1962]
Folder 13: Butler, Lawrence, “REPORT TO THE DIRECTOR: On holdings at Dumbarton Oaks of material pertaining to the church of Hagia Sophia in Istanbul” - Contains a report submitted by Lawrence Butler to Robert W. Thompson in February 1985
Folder 14: Correspondence from the Papers of Robert Woods Bliss and Mildred Barnes Bliss, ca. 1860-1969, Harvard University Archives - Contains copies of correspondence between Thomas Whittemore and Robert and Mildred Bliss from 1937 to 1941